<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<sect1 id="releasehistory">
	<title>Release history</title>

	<sect2 id="v1_4_0">
		<title>Version 1.4.0 (XX XXXXXX 2015)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Added option to export library for more easy sharing.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Fixed bug 6 at Google Code. When a snippets had an empty first line it could not be saved.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Removed all references to Google Code because that <ulink url="http://google-opensource.blogspot.nl/2015/03/farewell-to-google-code.html">service is retiring</ulink>. All things that were on Google Code have been moved to <ulink url="https://github.com/ffes/nppsnippets">GitHub</ulink>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Internally use SqliteDB-class to communicate with the database.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Added option <computeroutput>ToolbarIcon</computeroutput> to ini-file to hide the icon from the toolbar.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Fixed issue that sometimes new libraries and/or new snippets could not be added.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v1_3_0">
		<title>Version <ulink url="https://github.com/ffes/nppsnippets/releases/tag/v1.3.0">1.3.0</ulink> (June 2013, never officially release)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Fixed problem with inserting UTF snippets (<ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/nppsnippets/issues/detail?id=3">issue #3</ulink>).</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Fixed wrong title of Import Library dialog.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Fixed some potential bugs found when trying to fix GCC compilation.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Converted the documentation from ODT to DocBook. Because of that an <ulink url="http://www.fesevur.com/docbook/nppsnippets">on-line version</ulink> of the documentation is available as well.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Upgrade to SQLite version 3.8.0.2</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v1_2_0">
		<title>Version <ulink url="https://github.com/ffes/nppsnippets/releases/tag/v1.2.0">1.2.0</ulink> (8 January 2013)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>There was an inconsistency between the documentation and code about the name of the option to specify your custom path for the database. Use DBFile from now on. For backwards compatibility the DBPath entry will still be recognized.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>When a snippets creates a new document and the current document is empty, it reuses the current one and does not start a new.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Added Duplicate snippet function to context menu.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>New (simple) templates library.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Upgrade to SQLite version 3.7.15.1</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v1_1_0">
		<title>Version 1.1.0 (13 December 2011)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>You can now add a new snippet to a library based upon the current selection or based upon the content of the clipboard. Right-click the snippets list to use these items.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Installation has been improved. A template database is provided and when the plug-in tries to find an existing database and it can't find it, it copies this template database to the AppData plugin-config directory.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The About dialog now shows the change-log.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>When you upgrade the very first time the change-log for the current version will be shown.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>When you didn't select a specific library for a certain language, the automatic selection of the library is improved. The first language specific library is preferred over the first general library.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Resized the edit snippet dialog.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Upgrade to SQLite version 3.7.9</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Moved the download to <ulink url="https://code.google.com/p/nppsnippets/">Google code</ulink>. This gives me statistics about downloads and an issue tracker. The project's <ulink url="http://www.fesevur.com/nppsnippets">web page</ulink> stays where it is.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v1_0_0">
		<title>Version 1.0.0 (6 September 2011)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>The selection or cursor position are now restored after inserting a snippet.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v0_7_1">
		<title>Version 0.7.1 (28 August 2011)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Fixed a bug in the dialog to edit the languages for a certain library. This bug could cause a problem that libraries turn invisible, since all the records in LibraryLang table for that library were deleted and no new records were added.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Added a JavaScript - Math library.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v0_7_0">
		<title>Version 0.7.0 (1 August 2011)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>A user interface for editing the language selection for libraries has been added. You need at least Notepad++ version 5.93 for this feature.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>You can import a library from another NppSnippet database.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Start a new document for a certain snippets, and allow that snippet to set the language of that new document. There were already fields in the database for this. It can be very useful to start a new CSS-file or JavaScript-file from HTML, etc.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Added an option DBPath to the ini-file to override the default location of the database. Made this mainly for my own testing, but maybe it is useful for others as well (corporate database). You need to manually edit the ini-file to use this.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Added an icon to the tab of the docking interface.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Upgrade to SQLite version 3.7.7.1</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v0_6_0">
		<title>Version 0.6.0 (15 June 2011)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>It is now possible to add, edit or delete the snippets and the libraries from within Notepad++. It is not yet possible to edit the languages for a library.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Added a new ANSI-characters library for all languages.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Deleted the useless General library.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Upgrade to SQLite version 3.7.6.3</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v0_5_0">
		<title>Version 0.5.0 (21 December 2010)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Upgrade to SQLite version 3.7.4</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The focus is returned to the Scintilla window at start-up and after inserting a snippet.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The plug-in remembers if it is shown.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Added another special language to the table LibraryLang: Lang = -2. Libraries with this language will always be shown for all languages.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The languages last used is now stored in a separate table. The database schema version is 3. With this the libraries with special languages (negative language ID's) can be remembered as last used as well.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Error message when the database can not be opened.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v0_4_0">
		<title>Version 0.4.0 (8 April 2010)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>The database schema is updated and is now at version 2. The most important difference is that the "language" and "last used" field of the library are now in a separate table, allowing it to be one-to-many. Existing databases will be converted automatically to the new schema.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>When there are multiple libraries for a language, changing to another library works and the last used library is remembered.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The plug-in now first tries to find the database in the user's plug-in config directory. On my Windows XP machine that is C:\Documents and Settings\Frank\Application Data\Notepad++\plugins\config. If the database can't be found there it looks in the plugin\config directory in the Notepad++ installation directory, in my case C:\Program Files\Notepad++\plugins\Config.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Small improvements to the About dialog.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>There are now 4 HTML libraries, 1 PHP libraries, 1 XML library and 1 (rather useless) General library</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v0_3_0">
		<title>Version 0.3.0 (10 February 2010)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>First alpha version, released under the GPL2 license.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The basics work, no User Interface yet to edit the snippets</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="v0_1_0">
		<title>Version 0.1.0 (22 January 2010)</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Internal proof of concept.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>

</sect1>
